Preliminary Guide to the W. D. Davies papers, 1940-1987
Duke University. University Archives
W. D. Davies papers 1940-1987
Duke University. University Archives
Davies, W. D. (William David), 1911-2001
76.5 linear feet Extent: 76,500 Items
W. D. (William David) Davies (1911-2001) served as a Professor at Duke University Divinity School, from 1950 to 1955 and was George Washington Ivey Professor of Advanced Studies and Research in Christian Origins from 1966 to 1981. The collection features correspondence, course materials, writings, subject files, sermon notes, and research notes of W. D. Davies. Major research subjects include the New Testament, Christian theology, Judaism, and the issue of territorial imperative with regard to land.
UA.29.02.0016
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
Portions of these materials are restricted by donor request.
Unprocessed materials are closed pending processing.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The W. D. Davies papers were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1984-2001.
Biographical Note
W. D. (William David) Davies was born in Wales, United Kingdom, and educated at the University of Wales (B.A. 1934, B.D. 1938) and Cambridge University (B.A. 1940, M.A. 1942). Davies received his doctorate (D.D. operis causa 1948) from the University of Wales.
In 1941, Davies was ordained into the Congregational Church at Fowlmere, England. He taught at Yorkshire United College, Bradford, from 1946 to 1950 before moving to Duke for five years as a professor of Biblical theology (1950 to 1955). From 1955 through 1959 he was professor of religion at Princeton University, leaving to become Edward Robinson Professor of Biblical Theology at Union Theological Seminary in New York, as well as adjunct professor at Columbia University. He rejoined the Duke faculty in 1966 as George Washington Ivey Professor of Advanced Studies and Research in Christian Origins. He stayed until his retirement in 1981. He then became the Bradford Professor at Texas Christian University in Fort Worth, Texas and in 1986-87 he was a Fellow of Clare Hall, Cambridge, UK. He also taught at the University of California at Berkeley and at the University of Strasboroug, France.
Davies held numerous fellowships and received several awards and honors. He was a Fellow of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences, a Corresponding Fellow of the British Academy, (from which he also received the Burkitt Medal in Biblical Studies), an Honorary Fellow of Cambridge University's Fitzwilliam College, a Fellow of the Bellagio Center, Italy, and Fellow of the American Academy of Jewish Research. He was a recipient of two Guggenheim Fellowships and received honorary doctoral degrees from the University of St. Andrews, the Pacific School of Religion, Uppsala University and the University of Wales. Davies also served as honorary president of the Society for Biblical Literature and President of the Society of New Testament Studies (1976). He was a member of the executive committee of the World Congress of Jewish Studies, Jerusalem (1965).
Some of his published works include Paul and Rabbinic Judaism (1948), The Setting of the Sermon on the Mount (1966), and The Gospel and the Land: Early Christianity and Jewish Territorial Doctrine (1974). His popular Invitation to the New Testament (1966) was a Religion section of Book of the Month Club. He was also co-editor of the Cambridge History of Judaism and along with a former student published an International Critical Commentary on Matthew (3 vols).
Collection Overview
Correspondence, manuscript materials, article reprints, student papers, lecture notes, course reading materials, sermon notes, student notebooks relating to courses taken at the University of Wales Memorial College in Brecon, general research subject files, research notes relating to teaching at Duke University, Columbia University, Princeton, and Texas Christian College.
Subject Headings
Bible. N.T. -- Introductions; Bible. N.T. -- Criticism, interpretation, etc.; Bible -- Theology -- History of doctrines; Bible -- Theology -- Study and teaching; Church -- Sermons; Congregational Church in England and Wales -- Clergy; Davies, W. D. (William David), 1911-2001; Duke University. Divinity School; Duke University -- Faculty; Education (Christian theology); Judaism -- History -- Post-exile period, 586 B.C.-210 A.D.; Judaism -- Relations -- Christianity; Palestine in the Bible; Palestine in Christianity -- History of doctrines -- Early church, ca. 30-600 A.D.; Palestine in Judaism; Religion -- Study and teaching; Sermon on the Mount -- Criticism, interpretation, etc.
Related Material
Divinity School records, 1925-2005.
University Archives. Duke University.
Contents of Collection
- Container List, 51 Boxes
  - The Gospel and the Land-drafts, notes (Box 1)
  - Jerusalem and the Land in the Christian tradition-drafts, notes (Box 2)
  - The Jewish State in the Hellenistic World (Box 2)
  - The Territorial Dimension of Judaism (Box 2)
  - Cambridge History of Judaism (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous Course materials, 1967 (Box 3)
  - General research: Judeo-Christian relations (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous sermon and lecture notes (Box 4)
  - Lecture notes (Box 5)
  - Student papers (Box 5)
  - Pantyfedwen Lecture (Wales) (Box 5)
  - Paul and the Law (Box 5)
  - The New Creation (sermon collection) (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous papers (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous lecture notes (Box 6)
  - Cambridge History of Judaism (CHJ) (Box 7)
  - Personal and professional correspondence, arranged by date (Box 8)
  - Sermons preached in Fowlmere, England, 1941-1946 (Box 9)
  - Kearns Lecture, Duke University (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1967-1968 (Box 9)
  - Cambridge History of Judaism, volume 1 (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous research articles in Italian (Box 10)
  - General correspondence, 1973-1978 (A89-70) (Box 11)
  - General correspondence, 1978-1981 (Box 12)
  - People/project files (A-G) (Box 13)
  - Vita (Box 13)
  - People/project files (H-P) (Box 14)
  - People/project files (Q-Z) (Box 15)
  - Cambridge History of Judaism correspondence, 1971-1980 (Box 16)
  - Cambridge History of Judaism, general manuscript material, 1980-1986 (Box 17)
  - Cambridge History of Judaism, general manuscript material, 1981-1988 (Box 18)
  - Cambridge History of Judaism, general manuscript material, volumes I-II (Box 19)
  - Cambridge History of Judaism, general manuscript material, volumes III-IV (Box 20)
  - Aboth (Box 21)
  - Territory (Box 21)
  - Holy Land Colloquium, 1975 (Box 21)
  - Miscellaneous research papers (authored by colleagues) (Box 21)
  - Daube writings (Box 22)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence (Box 22)
  - NEH Seminar information and applications, 1982 (Box 22)
  - Miscellaneous research papers (authored by colleagues) (Box 23)
  - Student papers, ca 1960-1986 (Box 23)
  - General research subject files (bulk 1973-1974) (Box 24)
  - University Research Council (Box 24)
  - Travel expenses (Box 24)
  - Grants, 1981-1982 (Box 24)
  - Course outlines (Box 25)
  - General research subject files, bulk 1973-1974 (Box 25)
  - Personal files ("from desk") (Box 26)
  - General research subject files (Box 26)
  - Cambridge History of Judaism, general manuscript material, ca 1967 (Box 27)
  - Sermon notes (Box 27)
  - Miscellaneous articles (Box 27)
  - Lecture notes (Box 28)
  - Sermon notes (Box 28)
  - Reprints (Box 28)
  - Paul, Pauline doctrine (Box 29)
  - Mormonism (Box 29)
  - Lecture notes (Box 29)
  - Miscellaneous writings (Box 29)
  - Miscellaneous research papers (authored by colleagues): A-B (Box 30)
  - Miscellaneous research papers (authored by colleagues): C-Di (Box 31)
  - Miscellaneous research papers (authored by colleagues): Do-G (Box 32)
  - Miscellaneous research papers (authored by colleagues): H-K (Box 33)
  - Miscellaneous research papers (authored by colleagues): L-M (Box 34)
  - Miscellaneous research papers (authored by colleagues): Sch-St (Box 35)
  - Miscellaneous research papers (authored by colleagues): St-W (Box 36)
  - Miscellaneous reprints (Box 37)
  - Course teaching notes (Box 38)
  - Introduction to Theory (Box 38)
  - Cambridge History of Judaism, volumes II-IV (Box 39)
  - International Critical Commentary, volume II (Box 39)
  - International Critical Commentary, volumes I-II (Box 40)
  - Book reviews of works by Davies (Box 41)
  - Details of appointments at Duke, Berkeley, and Princeton (Box 41)
  - Conference and lecture notes (Box 41)
  - Commentary on Matthew (Box 42)
  - Japan correspondence (Box 42)
  - Miscellaneous writings (Box 42)
  - International Critical Commentary, galley proofs (Box 43)
  - Student notebooks (at Brecon), ca 1930 (Box 44)
  - Student notebooks (at Brecon), ca 1930 (Box 45)
  - Correspondence P-Sch (Box 46)
  - Correpsondence N-O (Box 47)
  - Torah Min Hashamayim (Box 48)
  - Society of Biblical Literature certificate, 1976 (Box 48)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence (mostly 1996-1997) (Box 48)
  - Draft of Reflections on Aspects of the Jewish Background of the Gospel of John (Box 48)
  - Miscellaneous writings and correspondence (mostly 1996-1997) (Box 49)
  - Article reprints (Box 49)
  - Sermon at Princeton University, 1985 (Box 49)
  - Bibliography (Box 49)
  - Mystical Antisemitism (Box 49)
  - Reviews of Cambridge History of Judaism (Box 49)
  - The Shroud of Turin (by colleagues) (Box 50)
  - Miscellaneous reprints (Box 50)
  - Correspondence (mostly 1992-1993) (Box 50)
  - Reflections of Judaism (Box 50)
  - Contemporary Quest for the Historical Jesus (Box 50)
  - Framed photographs (Box 50)
  - Reprints, 1995 (Box 50)
  - Compositional History of Q, draft (Box 51)
  - Paul and the New Exodus (Box 51)
  - Reflections on Aspects of the Jewish Background of the Gospel of John (Box 51)
  - Then and There (Box 51)
  - The Jewish Sources of Matthew's Messianism (Box 51)
  - The Intertextual Jesus: Scripture in Q (Box 51)